<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<thesis xmlns="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd">
		<title>2p or not 2p:The 14O(?,2p) 16O Reaction Rate and Its Implications on Nova and X-ray burst Nucleosynthesis</title><creator>Dessieux, Jr., Luc L.</creator><date.created>2002-12-01T08:00:00Z</date.created><thesis.degree.level>Thesis</thesis.degree.level><thesis.degree.name>Master of Science</thesis.degree.name><thesis.degree.discipline>Physics</thesis.degree.discipline><contributor>Mike Guidry</contributor><contributor>Soren Sorensen, Michael Smith, C.C. Shih, Raphael Hix</contributor><subject>Physics</subject><description.abstract>&lt;p&gt;During explosive hydrogen burning, the catalytic CNO cycle suffers depletion by additional thermonuclear capture reactions on the members of the cycle. This " break out" from the ?-limited CNO cycle has been suggested to occur in novae and X-ray bursts for temperatures greater than 0.4 GK [3,26,28]. At these temperatures ? captures can occur on the CNO waiting point isotopes through the nuclear reactions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;14O(?,p) 17F, 15O(?,?) 19Ne, and 18Ne(?,?) 21Na [3]. An additional reaction, 14O(?,2p)16O has been suggested as a possible break out path from the CNO cycle [49]. To investigate the astrophysical significance of the 14O(?,2p)16O reaction for the isotopes that are synthesized during novae outbursts and X-ray bursts, the unknown rate of this new reaction and the accepted rate of 14O(?,p) 17F have been varied using a scaling factor from negligible (10-9 of the 14O(?,p) 17F accepted rate), to a value exceeding the accepted 14O(?,p) 17F rate by a factor of 103. If this new rate is found to have significant astrophysical implications, it could be investigated with a radioactive beam at the Oak Ridge National Laboratorys Holifield Radioactive Beam facility. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a nova occurring on a 1.35 M